Guide to the University Archives Photograph Collection, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences Photographs, circa 1900 - 1992 UA 023.006
Special Collections Research Center
University Archives Photograph Collection, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences Photographs
Bulk, 1980-1987
circa 1900-1992
UA 023.006
Special Collections Research Center
1.0 Linear feet 2 archival boxes
2 archival boxes
As a land-grant institution, North Carolina State University has had agricultural study as an integral part of instruction since its beginning in 1887. In 1917, the first dean of agriculture took office, and the School of Agriculture was established in 1923. The name was changed to School of Agriculture and Life Sciences in 1964, and finally to College of Agriculture and Life Sciences in 1987. As of 2009, the College consists of 22 academic and extension departments, and runs the North Carolina Agricultural Research Service, the current name of the former Agricultural Experiment Station. The College continues to strive to meet its three primary functions -- teaching, research, and extension -- as first laid out over a century ago.
The University Archives Photograph Collection, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences Photographs contain photographs, negatives, and contact sheets documenting the people, departments, research, and activities relating to the College. The photographs are organized into the following series: General, Faculty and Staff, Buildings, Laboratories, Equipment and Machinery, Students – General, Students – Academic Life, Agriculture, Livestock, Biological Science, Environmental Science, Food Science, Gifts and Awards, Exhibitions and Displays, Agricultural Fair, Agricultural Information, F. H. Jeter, National Farm and Home Tour, Research, Other Programs, and Communication Services. For photographs of Agricultural Extension and Research Services, see UA 023.007.
Historical Note
As a land-grant institution, North Carolina State University has had agricultural study as an integral part of instruction since its beginning in 1887. In 1917, the first dean of agriculture took office, and the School of Agriculture was established in 1923. The name was changed to School of Agriculture and Life Sciences in 1964, and finally to College of Agriculture and Life Sciences in 1987.
The earliest courses of at NCSU were only in agriculture and mechanics, with classes in the former category consisting of "general agriculture, horticulture, arboriculture, and botany." Gradually, as the curriculum expanded, sets of classes were organized into "faculties" and then departments. Professors named to head these faculties or departments were usually given titles according to their specialty, such as Arborist or Agronomist. Additionally, experimental and practical work at the North Carolina Experiment Station and the Extension Service was increasingly undertaken by State College personnel.
With the reorganization of campus and academic administration came a shuffling of the curriculum within the new Agricultural School. Programs, or "instructional areas" were reduced to six: Agronomy, Animal Industry, Botany, Horticulture, Poultry Science, and Zoology. At the same time, work at the Experiment Station and in the Extension Service was more fully integrated into these programs, and cooperation among the three branches of the School took off. This situation remained largely unchanged until the creation of a Forestry program in 1929, which eventually became the Division of Forestry in 1931. This name change resulted in another one, when in 1932 the School of Agriculture became the School of Agriculture and Forestry.
New programs were added through the 1930s and 1940s, but the organization of the School remained largely unchanged. Several changes occurred in 1950, however. The Division of Forestry was split from Agriculture, to become the new School of Forestry, with Agriculture reverting to its old designation, the School of Agriculture. The other change was the creation that same year of the Division of Biological Sciences, combining the Faculties of Botany, Entomology, Plant Pathology, and Zoology, adding Genetics in 1951. This set-up continued until 1958, when the Division was disbanded and its constituent parts granted Department status as individual units within the School of Agriculture. The 1950s also saw dramatic increases in budgets for research and teaching, and the first international effort for the School, the Peru Project, which started in 1955.
The 1960s brought another decade of change to the School, not least of which was another name change in 1964, becoming the School of Agriculture and Life Sciences. One prompt for the new name was an increase in the importance and development of the biological sciences, prompting the creation of the Institute of Biological Sciences in 1962, which in large part succeeded the disbanded Division of Biological Sciences. The Agricultural Policy Institute was created in 1960 in conjunction with the Kellogg Foundation, and worked with agricultural institutions across the south to address and mold public policy issues regarding southern agriculture.
The recent decades have seen steady growth in physical space, students, research, and funding. In 1987, a final name change occurred, and the School of Agriculture and Life Sciences became the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. In 2006 the Department of Botany was renamed the Department of Plant Biology. As of 2009, the College consists of 22 academic and extension departments, and runs the North Carolina Agricultural Research Service, the current name of the former Agricultural Experiment Station. The College continues to strive to meet its three primary functions -- teaching, research, and extension -- as first laid out over a century ago.
Scope and Content Note
The University Archives Photograph Collection, College of Agriculture and Life Sciences Photographs contain photographs, negatives, and contact sheets documenting the people, departments, research, and activities relating to the College. The organized into the following series: General, Faculty and Staff, Buildings, Laboratories, Equipment and Machinery, Students – General, Students – Academic Life, Agriculture, Livestock, Biological Science, Environmental Science, Food Science, Gifts and Awards, Exhibitions and Displays, Agricultural Fair, Agricultural Information, F. H. Jeter, National Farm and Home Tour, Research, Other Programs, and Communication Services. For photographs of Agricultural Extension and Research Services see UA 023.007.
Related Material
UA 023.007 Agricultural Extention and Research Service Photographs
Restrictions to Access
Collection is open for research; access requires at least 24 hours advance notice.
Jeter, F. H. (Frank Hamilton), 1891-1955; North Carolina State University--Departments--History.; North Carolina State University--History--20th century.; North Carolina State University--Students--History.; North Carolina State University. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences--Faculty--History.; North Carolina State University. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences--History.; North Carolina State University. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences--Photographs.; North Carolina State University. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Agronomy--History.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Animal Science.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Botany--History.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Communication Services.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Crop Science.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Entomology.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Food Science.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Horticultural Science.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Plant Pathology.; North Carolina State University. Dept. of Zoology.; North Carolina State University. Soil Science Dept.; Southeastern Plant Environment Laboratory.; Agriculture--North Carolina--History--20th century; Agriculture--North Carolina--Photographs; Agriculture--Research--North Carolina; Agriculture--Study and teaching (Higher)--North Carolina; Botany--Research--North Carolina; Botany--Study and teaching--North Carolina; Cattle--Study and teaching--North Carolina; Chickens; Corn; Cotton; Crop science--Research--North Carolina--History; Crops; Dairy farms; Dairying; Entomology--Research--North Carolina; Entomology--Study and teaching--North Carolina; Farmers--North Carolina; Forestry schools and education--North Carolina; Forests and forestry--Research--North Carolina; Grain; Horticulture--Research--North Carolina; Horticulture--Study and teaching (Higher)--North Carolina; Livestock; Livestock--Study and teaching--North Carolina; Photographs; Poultry; Poultry--Study and teaching (Higher)--North Carolina; Soil science--Research--North Carolina; Swine--Study and teaching--North Carolina; Tobacco farmers; Tobacco industry--North Carolina--History; Tobacco workers--North Carolina; Tobacco--North Carolina; Tobacco--Research--North Carolina; Zoology--Study and teaching--North Carolina
- General, Bulk, 1982-1984; circa 1920-1994
  - Non-University Agriculture (moved from UA 023.024) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - SALS Revue, Spring 1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Faculty and Staff, circa 1900-1988
  - Faculty and Staff (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Buildings, 1968, 1970, undated
  - Food Science Building and Phytotron (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Laboratories, Bulk, 1946; circa 1920,1921,1946,1976,
  - Laboratories (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Equipment and Machinery, 1915,1936
  - Equipment and Machinery (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Students. General, 1909,1939,1941,1949-1950
  - Students (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Students. Academic Life, circa 1920,1936,1937,1948
  - Students (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Agriculture, 1902,1938,1941,1946,1961,1962,circa 1970,1970,1974, undated
  - Agronomy Department (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Horticulture (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Livestock, circa 1900,1928,1950, circa 1960
  - Animal Science (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Biological Science, Bulk, 1954-1960; 1909-1980
  - Botany and Plant Pathology (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Zoology Department (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Environmental Science, circa 1930,1938-1939, circa 1970
  - General (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Food Science, Bulk, 1947; 1947-1963
  - General (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Gifts and Awards, Bulk, 1985; 1981-1992
  - North Carolina Safety Council Awards, 1981-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Exhibitions and Displays, Bulk, 1984; 1922-1984, undated
  - Department of Plant Pathology History Display, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibtions and Displays (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Agricultural Fair, Bulk, 1927; circa 1920-1940, undated
  - General (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Agricultural Information, Bulk, 1980; 1963,1980
  - General (Box 2, Folder 5)
- F. H. Jeter, circa 1940
  - F. H. Jeter (Box 2, Folder 6)
- National Farm and Home Tour, circa 1940
  - NBC Radio Broadcast (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Research, Bulk, 1977; circa 1950-1987, undated
  - General (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - General (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Other Programs, Bulk, 1987; 1987
  - Science in the Classroom, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Communication Services, Bulk, 1984; 1959-1989, undated
  - F-S (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Scope and Contents note
    Fellowships, Greenhouse Tomatoes, Hog Farming, People, Pigs, Soil
  - S (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Soil, Strawberries, Swine
  - T (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Target 2, Tobacco
  - T (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Tobacco
  - T-W, Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Scope and Content Note
    Tobacco, Tomatoes, Turf Grass, Veterinary Medical Association, Watermelon, Weeds, Miscellaneous
  - Research Station Descriptions (Box 2, Folder 16)